Today starts a two-lecture sequence on the topic of hashing,
今天我们花两个课时来学习哈希表
which is a really great technique that shows up in a lot of places.
哈希是一项强大的技术  在很多地方都有用到
So we're going to introduce it
那我们用一个问题引入
through a problem that comes up often in compilers
这个问题经常出现在编译器里
called the symbol table problem.
就是“符号表问题”了
And the idea is that we have a table S
现在有一个表S
holding n records where each record,
里面放着n条记录  对于每条记录
just to be a little more explicit here.
这里要说得更清楚一点
So each record typically has a bunch of,
每条记录都会有一些
this is record x. x is usually a pointer to the actual data.
这是记录x  x通常是一个指向实际数据的指针
So when we talk about the record x,
当我们提到记录x的时候
what it usually means some pointer to the data
它通常代表着指向数据x的指针
And in the data, in the record,
在记录里  而不是数据中
so this is a record, there is a key called a key of x
这是一条记录  这个键叫记录x的键
In some languages it's key,
在某些编程语言里
it's x dot key or x arrow key,
它用x.key或x→key表示
OK, are other ways that that will be denoted in some languages.
这不过是不同语言里  不同的表示而已
And there's usually some additional data called satellite data,
通常还会有一些额外的数据  称为卫星数据
which is carried around with the key.
这些数据属于键的附加数据
This is also true in sorting, but usually you're sorting records.
排序时也有这种情况  只不过你是对记录排序
You're not sorting individual keys.
而不是对键排序
And so the idea is that we have a bunch of operations
现在我们要进行一系列的操作
that we would like to do on this data on this table.
我们想对这张表上的数据进行一系列的操作
So we want to be able to insert an item x into the table,
想要在表里插入一条记录x
which just essentially means that
本质上讲
we update the table by adding the element x.
就是通过添加元素x  来更新这个表
We want to be able to delete an item from the table
我们想要从表里删除一条记录
-- -- so removing the item x from the set
也就是从集合里移除记录x
and we want to be able to search for a given key.
我们还想要用给定的键k进行搜索
So this returns the value x such that key of x is equal to k,
那么当x的键值为k时  这个函数返回x
where it returns nil if there's no such x.
如果没有相应的记录则返回nil（注：空值）
So be able to insert items in, delete them and also look to see
现在我们已经能添加记录、删除记录
if there's an item that has a particular key
还能查找有特定键值的记录
So notice that delete doesn't take a key. Delete takes a record.
要注意  删除不是删除键值  而是删除整条记录
OK, so if you want to delete something of a particular key
好了   如果你想删除有特定键值的记录
and you don't happen to have a pointer to it
而又没有它的位置指针
you have to say let me search for it and then delete it.
那就必须先把它找出来  然后再删除
So these, whenever you have a set operations,
当一个集合可以进行操作时
where operations that change the set like in certain delete,
就例如删除之类的改变集合的操作
we call it a dynamic set.
把这个集合称之为“动态集”
So these two operations make the set dynamic
这两种操作将集合动态化了
It changes over time.
这些集合会因时而变
Sometimes you want to build a fixed data structure.
有时你想要建一个固定的数据结构
It's going to be a static set.
你需要一个静态的集合
All you're going to do is do things like look it up and so forth.
你所需要做的就是  诸如“查阅”之类的操作
But most often, it turns out that in programming and so forth,
但在更多的情况下  在像编程之类的工作中
we want to have the set be dynamic.
我们希望集合是动态的
Want to be able to add elements to it,
想要向它添加记录
delete elements to it and so forth
或者删除记录等等
And there may be other operations that modify the set,
还有一些别的能修改集合的操作
modify membership in the set.
或者改变集合里的成员关系
So the simplest implementation for this is actually often overlooked.
其实最简单的实现  也最容易被忽视
I'm actually surprised how often people use more complicated data structures
实际上  我对人们常使用复杂的数据结构感到惊讶
when this simple data structure will work.
其实简单的数据结构已经能完成工作
It's called a direct access table. Doesn't always work.
这个简单的结构叫“直接映射表”  它不是总能起作用
I'll give the conditions where it does.
但我这里会列出它能发挥作用的情况
So it works when the keys are drawn from our small distribution.
当键值的分布比较小的时候  它就能发挥作用
So suppose the keys are drawn from a set U of m elements.
就假设这些键是来自一个有m个元素的集合U
OK, zero to m minus one.
从0到m-1
And we're going to assume the keys are distinct.
我们假定这些键是相互独立
So the way a direct access table works
直接映射表是这样工作的
is that you set up an array T from zero to m minus one
当你建立一个从0到m-1的数组T
to represent the dynamic set S
来表示动态集合S
such that T of k is going to be equal to x
这样的话  T[k]=x
if x is in the set and its key is k
当且仅当x在这个集合里  而且它的键值为k
and nil otherwise.
否则T[k]为空
So you just simply have an array
就例如你有一个数组
and if you have a record whose key is some value k,
你有一条记录  它的键是某个k值
the key is 15 say,
比如键值是15
then slot 15 if the element is there has the element.
如果存在某条记录的键值是15  那槽15就存在
And if it's not in the set, it's nil.
如果集合里没有键值为15的记录  那么槽15就是空的
Very simple data structure. OK, insertion.
非常简单的数据结构  首先插入
Just go to that location and set the value to the inserted value.
就是把相应位置的值设成要插入的值
For deletion, just remove it from there.
至于删除  就是直接移除那里的值
And to look it up, you just index it and see what's in that slot.
还有查看  就是通过索引来查看槽的内容
OK, very simple data structure.
非常简单的数据结构
All these operations, therefore,
所有的这些操作
take constant time in the worst case.
在最坏情况下的时间复杂度都是常数量
But as a practical matter,
但在实际应用上
the places you can use this strategy are pretty limited.
你能用到这个策略的地方却非常有限
What's the issue of limitation here?
这个数据结构的局限性是什么呢？
[Student]Inaudible.
[学生]。。。
But there's actually a more severe limitation.
但事实上它还有一个更严重的局限性
[Professor]Yeah. What does that mean, it's hard to draw?
[教授]你的意思是  它很难从表里取值？
No. Yeah. m minus one could be a huge number.
不  m-1可能是个很大的数
Like for example, suppose that I want to
比如  假设我想要
have my set drawn over 64 bit values.
我的集合的数据都是64位的值
OK, the things that I'm storing in my table
就是储存在我表里的东西
is a set of 64-bit numbers.
是一组长度为64位的数字
And so, maybe a small set.
然后  它可能只是一个小集合
Maybe we only have a few thousand of these elements.
可能我只有几千个元素
But they're drawn from a 64-bit value.
但它们有64位的值
Then this strategy requires me to have an array
然而这个数据结构却要求我
that goes from zero to 2 to the 64th minus one.
有一个从0到2^64 - 1的数组
How big is 2^64 minus one? Approximately?
2^64-1有多大？用手指头算算？
It's like big. It's like 18 quintillion or something.
这个数很庞大  大约有1800亿个亿那么大
I mean, it's zillions literally because it's like
我的意思是  大到你不相信
it's beyond the illions we normally use.
已经超过了我们经常用的数以亿计的概念
Not a billion or a trillion. It's 18 quintillion.
不是十亿也不是万亿  是1800亿个亿
OK, so that's a really big number.
确实是一个超级大的数
So, or even worse, suppose the keys
更糟糕的是  假设这些键
were drawn from character strings,
取自字符串
so people's names or something.
比如人名之类的
This would be an awful way to have to represent it.
情况就会变得非常糟糕
Because most of the table would be empty
因为这样的话  表就有大量的空槽
for any reasonable set of values you would want to keep.
远超出我们需要保存的数据量
So the idea is we want to try to keep something
但我们所希望的是保存东西之余
that's going to keep the table small,
还能让表的规模尽可能的小
while still preserving some of the properties.
同时还然能保留某些特性
And that's where hashing comes in.
这时我们就需要哈希表出场了
So hashing is we use a hash function H which maps the keys randomly
所谓的哈希法  就是用一个哈希函数H来随机映射那些键
And I'm putting that in quotes
我帮"随机"加个引号
because it's not quite at random. Into slots table T.
因为它不是完全的随机  把键映射到哈希表T的槽
So we call each of the array indexes here a slot.
这种情况下数组的索引称为“槽”
So you can just sort of think of it as a big table
你可以把它想成一个大的表
and you've got slots in the table where you're storing your values.
表里的槽储存的就是你的数值
And so, we may have a big universe of keys. Let's call that U.
我们可能有一个很大的键的全域，我们称之为U
And we have our table over here
这里有一个表
that we've set up that has -- -- m slots.
由我们建立的  有m个槽的表
And so we actually have then a set that
实际上这里有一个集合
we're actually going to try to represent S,
我们用S来表示
which is presumably a very small piece of the universe.
假设是这全域里很小的一块
And what we'll do is we'll take an element from here
我们要做的是  从这里取出一个键
and map it to let's say to there and take another one
映射到哈希表的那里  然后再取另外一个
and we apply the hash function to the element.
我们将这个键代入哈希函数
And what the hash function is going to give us
然后哈希函数将会返回给我们
is it's going to give us a particular slot.
会给我们一个特定的槽
Here's one that might go up here.
这个键可能会映射到上面这里
Might have another one over here that goes down to there.
另外一个键可能映射到下面这里
And so, we get it to distribute the elements over the table.
这样  我们将键分布到整个表里
So what's the problem that's going to occur as we do this?
那映射的过程中会发生什么问题呢？
So far, I've been a little bit lucky.
到目前为止  我们都比较幸运
What's the problem potentially going to be?
但潜在的问题是什么呢？
Yeah, when two things are in S, more specifically,
是的  当有两个键在S里  更准确地说
get assigned to the same value.
被赋予了同样的哈希值
So I may have a guy here and he gets mapped to the same slot
某个键有可能映射到一个槽
that somebody else has already been mapped to.
但这个槽已经有另外一个键映射在那了
And when this happens, we call that a collision.
当这种情况发生时  我们称之为“碰撞”
So we're trying to map these things down into a small set
我们试图将这些键映射到一个小的集合里
but we could get unlucky in our mapping,
但我们可能在映射过程中遭遇不顺
particularly if we map enough of these guys.
尤其是  当我们映射足够多的键时
They're not going to fit.
它们不会全部一一对应
So when a record -- -- to be inserted maps
当一个记录要插入映射表时
to an already occupied slot
却被映射到一个早已有记录的槽时
-- -- a collision occurs.
碰撞发生了
OK. So looks like this method's no good.
所以  看起来这个方法并不是很好
But no, there's a pretty simple thing we can do.
但实际上  我们可以对它做些小改动
What should we do when two things map to the same slot?
当两个键映射到同一个槽时  我们该怎么办？
If we want to represent the whole set,
我们要表示整个集合
but you can't lose any data, can't treat it like a cache.
你不能丢弃任何数据  不能把它当成缓存
In a cache what you do is it uses a hashing scheme,
虽然缓存用的也是哈希结构
but in a cache, you just kick it out
但在缓存里  你只是剔除数据
because you don't care about representing a set precisely.
因为你不在乎数据集的完整性
But in a hash table you're programming,
但当你的编程用到了哈希表时
you often want to make sure that the values you have
你希望你用到的数据
are exactly the values in the sets
就是集合里的这些数据
so you can tell whether something belongs to the set or not.
这样你才能分辨哪些数据是属于这个集合的
So what's a good strategy here?
那么一个好的策略是什么呢？
Yeah. Create a list for each slot and just put all the elements
对每个槽创建一个链表  把所有映射到这个槽的元素
that hash to the same slot into the list.
都存到这个槽的链表里面去
And that's called resolving collisions by chaining.
这就是用来解决碰撞的链接法
And the idea is to link records in the same slot ---- into a list.
方法是把相同的哈希值的记录放到一个链表里储存
So for example, imagine this is
打个比方  想像一下
my hash table and this for example is slot i.
这是我的哈希表  这个是槽i
I may have several things that are,
这里是一些键
so I'm going to put the key value -- -- have several things
我先把把键值写进去——这些属于S集合的键
that may have been inserted into this table that are elements of S.
之前就已经插入到这个表里了
And what I'll do is just link them together.
我们要做的只是将他们链接起来
OK, so nil pointer here.
这里是个空指针
And this is the satellite data and these are the keys.
这些是卫星数据，这些是键
So if they're all linked together in slot i,
如果它们全部都是链接到槽i的话
then the hash function applied to 49 has got to be
那么运用哈希函数,h(49)
equal to the hash function of 86
就等于h(86)
is equal to the hash function of 52, which equals what?
也等于h(52)  也就是多少呢？
There's only one thing I haven't. i.
就是我们一直没用到的数值，i
Good. Even if you don't understand it,
不错  即使你不理解它
your quizmanship should tell you.
你的做题的经验也会告诉你
He didn't mention i. That's equal to i.
他还没有用到i  那这里就应该用到i
So the point is when I hash 49,
我想说的是当我计算49的哈希值时
the hash of 49 produces me some index in the table, say i,
h(49)生成了哈希表的某个索引  比如i
and everything that hashes to that same location
而其它所有哈希值相同的键
is linked together into a list.
也都一起链接到一同一个链表里
Every record. Any questions about what the mechanics of this.
包括每个记录  对于这个机制还有什么问题没有？
I hope that most of you have seen this,
我希望你们大部分人  都已经（在书上）看过这些
seen hashing, basic hashing in 6.001, right?
在课程6.001里看过哈希  基础哈希  对吧？
They teach it in? They used to teach it 6.001.
在哪里讲到？他们以前在6.001讲过这个
Yeah. OK. Some people are saying maybe.
对，有人说是，也许是吧
They used to teach it.
他们以前讲过这个
Good. So let's analyze this strategy.
好的  我们来分析这个策略
The analysis. We'll first do worst case.
首先做最坏情况分析
So what happens in the worst case? With hashing?
最坏情况下会发生什么？  对哈希而言
Yeah, raise your hand so that I could call on you.
举起你的手  那样我才能叫你回答问题
Yeah. Yeah, all hash keys, well all, all the keys in S.
对  所有哈希键  所有S里的键
I happen to pick a set S where my hash function
我恰好选择了一个集合S  通过哈希函数
happens to map them all to the same value. That would be bad.
生成的哈希值都是一样的  那就非常糟糕
So every key hashes to the same slot.
所有键哈希映射到同一个槽
And so, therefore if that happens,
如果这种情况发生了
then what I've essentially built
那么本质上  我所建立的
is a fancy linked list for keeping this data structure.
就只是一个拥有这种数据结构的奇怪链表
All this stuff with the tables, the hashing, etc., irrelevant.
所有跟该哈希表相关的东西  哈希过程等等  都无关紧要了
All that matters is that I have a long linked list.
真正有用的  就只是这个长的链表而已
And then how long does an access take?
访问一次要花多少时间呢？
How long does it take me to insert something or well,
插入一些记录要花我多长时间  或者。。。
more importantly, to search for something.
更重要的是  查找要花多少时间
Find out whether something's in there. In the worst case
在最坏情况下  查看某个记录是否在表里
Yeah, it takes order n time.
是的  它需要的时间为θ(n)
Because they're all just a link, we just have a linked list.
因为全部都在一个链表里  我们只有一个链表
So access takes data n time
所以访问需要θ(n)
if as we assume the size of S is equal to n.
如果我们假设S的大小等于n
So from a worst case point of view, this doesn't look so attractive.
从最坏情况的角度来看  这个数据结构并不是很好
And we will see data structures
我们会看到其他数据结构
that in worst case do very well for this problem.
它们在最坏的情况下比哈希更出色
But they don't do as good as the average case of hashing.
但它们在平均情况下不如哈希好
So let's analyze the average case.
我们来分析一下平均情况
In order to analyze the average case, I have to,
为了分析平均情况  我必须。。。
whenever you have averages, whenever you have probability,
无论你是平均情况也好  其他可能情况也罢
you have to state your assumptions.
你必须声明你的假设
You have to say what is the assumption
对于系统的行为而言
about the behavior of the system.
你必须说清楚  假设条件是什么
And it's very hard to do that
这是非常难的
because you don't know necessarily what the hash function is.
因为你不知道哈希函数的必然性是什么
Well, let's imagine an ideal hash function.
我们来想像一个理想的哈希函数
What should an ideal hash function do?
一个理想的哈希函数要做什么呢？
Yeah, map the keys essentially at random to a slot.
对，将键基本随机映射到一个槽上
Should really distribute them randomly.
应该真正随机分布
So we call this the assumption -- of simple uniform hashing
我们把这种假设情况称为——简单均匀哈希
And what it means is that each key k in S is equally likely
它的意思是  每个属于集合S的键值K都有相同的几率
-- -- to be hashed to any slot in T
被哈希映射到表T的任意一个槽里
and we're actually have to make an independence assumption.
实际上  我们还有必要做个独立性的假设
Independent of where other records, other keys are hashed.
每个键与其他被哈希的记录或键之间相互独立
So we're going to make this assumption
我们要做的就是这种简单均匀哈希的假设
and includes an independence assumption.
而且还包含一个独立性假设
That if I have two keys the odds
那如果我有两个键
that they're hashed to the same place is therefore what?
它们被哈希映射到同一个槽的概率是多少呢？
What are the odds that two keys under this assumption
在我们刚才所说的这种假设下
are hashed to the same slot, if I have, say, m slots?
它们映射到同一个槽的概率是多少 假如我有m个槽的话？
One over m. What are the odds that one key is hashed to slot 15?
1/m， 那么一个键被哈希映射到槽15的概率又是多少？
One over m. Because they're being distributed,
也是1/m， 因为它们是独立的
but the odds in particular two keys
而特定的两个键
are hashed to the same slot, one over m.
被哈希映射到同一个槽的概率 也是1/m
So let's define. Is there a question?
有什么问题吗？
No. OK. The load factor of a hash table with n keys at m slots
没有 好的 我们定义一个存放n个键、有m个槽的哈希表
to be alpha which is equal to n over m,
它的装载因子是 α = n/m
which is also if you think about it,
如果你仔细想想
just the average number of keys per slot.
它就是  每个槽里键的平均数量
So alpha is the average number of keys per,
所以α是每个槽里键的平均数量
we call it the load factor of the table. OK.
我们把它称为哈希表的装载因子
How many on average keys do I have?
也就是平均每个槽有多少个键
So the expected, we'll look first at unsuccessful search time.
我们先看看  失败搜索的预计用时
So by unsuccessful search, I mean
所谓的“失败搜索”是指...
I'm looking for something that's actually not in the table.
我要查找的东西并不在哈希表里的
It's going to return nil. I look for a key that's not in the table.
最终返回结果是nil  因为搜索的键并不在表里
It's going to be what? It's going to be order.
那预计用时是多少？这等于...
Well, I have to do a certain amount of work
当然  即使搜索不到我们也要做一轮运算
just to calculate the hash function and so forth.
比如计算哈希值之类的
It's going to be order at least one plus,
所以 这至少等于θ(1 +...
then I have to search the list
因为我还要搜索这个链表
and on average how much of the list do I have to search?
平均情况下要搜索的链表有多大呢？
What's the cost of searching that list?
搜索这个链表的平均花费是多少？
On average. If I'm searching at random.
一般来说 假设是我们是随机地搜索
If I'm searching for a key that's not in the table.
如果我搜索的是一个并不存在于这个哈希表的键
Whichever one it is, I got to search to the end of the list, right?
那不管是哪个键 我都必须把整个链表搜索一遍 是吧？
So what's the average cost over all the slots in the table?
那整条链表搜索一遍平均花费是多少？
Alpha. Right? Alpha.
α？对 就是α
That's the average length of a list.
它是链表的平均长度
So this is essentially the cost of doing the hash
这里的“1”是指 把键指哈希映射到槽
and then accessing the slot
所需要的时间
and that is just the cost of searching the list.
而α是搜索槽对应的链表 所花费的时间
So the expected unsuccessful search time
所以预计失败搜索的时间
is proportional essentially to alpha
基本与α是成比例的
and if alpha's bigger than one, it's order alpha.
如果α大于1 这个近似于θ（α）
If alpha's less than one, it's constant.
如果α小于1 它近似于一个常数量
So when is the expected search time -- -- equal to order one?
什么情况下预计搜索时间  等于θ（1）
So when is this order one?
什么时候会是θ（1）
Simple questions, by the way.
顺便说一下 这是个简单的问题
I only ask simple questions. Some guys ask hard questions.
我问的问题都很简单 可能有些人会问很难的问题
[Professor]Yeah. Or in terms first we'll get there in two steps, OK.
[教授]或者我们先分两个步来解答这个问题
In terms of alpha, it's when?
α在什么情况下 搜索时间等于θ（1）
When alpha is constant. If alpha in particular is.
答案是α恰好是一个常数量时
Alpha doesn't have to be constant. It could be less than constant.
当然 α也可以不是常数量 它可能比常数量还要小
It's O of one, right. OK, or equivalently,
也就是α= O（1） 或者也可以说
which is what you said, if n is O of m.
正如你所说的 如果n＝O(m)
OK, which is to say if the number of elements in the table is order,
也就是说  如果哈希表里键的数量n
is upper bounded by a constant times m.
不会超过槽的数量m的常数倍
Then the search cost is constant.
那么搜索花费的时间就是一个常数量
So a lot of people will tell you oh,
所以很多人会跟你说
a hash table runs in constant search time.
一个哈希表的运行时间是固定值
OK, that's actually wrong.
实际上那是错误的
It depends upon the load factor of the hash table.
它其实取决于哈希表的装载因子
And people have made programming errors
正是由于对哈希表的这个错误理解
based on that misunderstanding of hash tables.
人们在编程时就会犯一些错误
Because they have a hash table that's too small
因为他们的哈希表太小了
for the number of elements they're putting in there.
相对于他们要放进去的键的数量而言没有帮助
Doesn't help. The number may in fact will grow with the,
键的数量有可能会增加
since this is one plus n over m, it actually grows with n.
因为这是θ（1+n/m）  它是随着n增加而增加的
So unless you make sure that m keeps up with n,
除非你能保证m跟n一起增长
this doesn't stay constant.
否则  θ并不保持常数量
Now it turns out for a successful search, it's also one plus alpha.
事实上 一个成功搜索的运行时间也是θ（1+α)
And for that you need to do a little bit more mathematics
但证明这个你必须做一点数学运算
because you now have to condition
因为这次的条件不同了
on searching for the items in the table.
这次搜索的数据是存在哈希表中的
But it turns out it's also one plus alpha
虽然结果也是1+α
and that you can read about in the book.
你可以从书里读到相关的内容
And also, there's a more rigorous proof of this.
当然也有一些更严格的证明
I sort of have glossed over the expectation stuff here,
不过我在这里就不列出完整的证明过程了
doing sort of a more intuitive proof.
只是给出一些直观上的解释
So both of those things you should look for in the book.
这些应该对照课本里的内容看一下
So this is one reason why hashing is such a popular method,
上述内容也是为什么哈希这么受欢迎的一个原因
is it basically lets you represent a dynamic set
主要是你能在θ（1）的运行时间内
with order one cost per operation,
完成动态集合里的操作
constant cost per operation, inserting, deleting and so forth,
比如插入、删除等 每个操作的运行时间都是一个常数量
as long as the table that you're keeping
只要你哈希表的大小
is not much smaller than the number of items
不要远小于你要放在里面
that you're putting in there.
所保存的记录个数
And then all the operations end up being constant time.
那么所有操作都只需一个常数量的运行时间
But it depends upon,
但很大程度上
strongly upon this assumption of simple uniform hashing.
这种情况是建立在“简单均匀哈希”的假设上
And so no matter what hash function you pick,
因为不论你用的是什么哈希函数
I can always find a set of elements that are going to hash,
我总是能找到一些元素
that that hash function is going to hash badly.
使得哈希映射出的结果很糟糕
I just could generate a whole bunch of them
例如我可以制造出一堆元素
and look to see where the hash function takes them
代入到哈希函数里 看看它们会被映射到哪个槽
and in the end pick a whole bunch that hash to the same place.
然而最后它们却都映射到了同一个槽里
We're actually going to see a way of countering that,
所以我们要反过来想什么是才好的哈希函数
but in practice people understand that most programs
但在实际应用中 我们知道绝大多数的程序用到的
that need to use things aren't really reverse engineering the hash function.
并不是真正由逆向工程得到的哈希函数
And so, there's some very simple hash functions
另外，有些非常简单的哈希函数
that seem to work fairly well in practice.
在现实中似乎能起到很好的作用
So in choosing a hash function
如何选择一个哈希函数
-- -- we would like it to distribute -- keys uniformly into slots
我们想要把键 均匀分布到槽里
and we also would like that regularity in the key distributions
而键本身的一些分布的特性
---- should not affect uniformity.
不会影响到它在哈希表中分布的均匀性
For example, a regularity that you often see is that
举个例子 你经常见的一个分布特性是
all the keys that are being inserted are even numbers.
所有插入的键值都是偶数
Somebody happens to have that property of his data,
碰巧某些人的数据有这样的属性
that they're only inserting even numbers.
他们只插入偶数值的键
In fact, on many machines, since they use byte pointers,
实际上 因为在很多机器上使用的是字节指针
if they're sorting things that are for example,
如果它们是按照...比如
indexes to arrays or something like that, in fact,
按照数组的索引来分类的话
they're numbers that are typically divisible by four. Or by eight.
这些数据大多数都会被分配到能被四或者被八整除的索引里
So you don't want regularity in the key distribution
你不希望键的这种特性
to affect the fact that you're distributing slots.
会影响到它在槽的分布均匀性
So probably the most popular method
那也许用于快速哈希函数里
that's used just for a quick hash function
最受欢迎的方法
is what's called the division method.
就是我们说的“除法哈希法”了
And the idea here is that
具体实现是这样的
you simply let h of k for a key equal k modulo m,
让 h(k)=k mod m （k对m取余）
where m is the number of slots in your table.
m 是哈希表里槽的数量
And this works reasonably well in practice,
实际上这个函数的实现很合理
but you want to be careful about your choice of modulus.
但你必须注意你选择的除数（即m）
In other words, it turns out it doesn't work well
换句话说 它并不是都能...
for every possible size of table you might want to pick.
适用于任意大小的哈希表
Fortunately when you're building hash tables,
幸运的是当你建立哈希表时
you don't usually care about the specific size of the table.
你通常并不关注哈希表的具体大小
If you pick it around some size, that's probably fine
如果你在某个值的附近取值 可能没问题
because it's not going to affect their performance.
因为这不会影响到运行效率
So there's no need to pick a specific value.
所以没必要选择一个具体的值
In particular, you don't want to pick ---- m with a small divisor
不过要注意，千万不要选择太小的m来做除数
and let me illustrate why that's a bad idea
让我解释一下为什么
for this particular hash function.
这种做法对这种除法哈希法不好
I should have said small divisor d.
我应该把这个小除数定义成d
So for example -- -- if D is two,
举个例子 如果d=2
in other words m is an even number,
也就是说m是一个偶数
and it turns out that we have the situation
如果恰好我们所说的那种情况发生了
I just mentioned, all keys are even,
所有的键都是偶数的
what happens to my usage of the hash table?
对哈希表的运作会产生什么影响？
So I have an even slot, even number of slots,
我有偶数个槽
and all the keys that the user of the hash table chooses
而所有用户选择的键
to pick happen to be even numbers,
也恰好都是偶数
what's going to happen in terms of my use of the hash table?
对哈希表的使用会发生什么事呢？
[Professor]Well, in the worst case,
[教授]在最坏情况下
[Professor]they are always all going to point in the same slot
[教授]无论我选择什么哈希函数
[Professor]no matter what hash function I pick.
[教授]所有键都映射指向同一个槽
[Professor]But here, let's say that, in fact,
[教授]但这里 假设
[Professor]my hash function does do a pretty good job of distributing,
[教授]一般情况下这个哈希函数的分布效果还不错
but I have this property. What's a property that's going to have
但对于这个特殊的性质 它又会导致怎样的结果？
no matter what set of keys I pick
不管我选择的是哪一组键
that satisfies this property?
只要它满足这一个性质
What's going to happen to the hash table?
那哈希表将变成什么样？
So, I have even number, mod an even number.
偶数对偶数取余
What does that say about the hash function?
哈希函数h(k)的值会是什么？
It's even, right? I have an even number mod. It's even.
是偶数 对吧？如果我用偶数对偶数取余，得数就会是偶数
So, what's going to happen to my use of the table?
那这对我使用哈希表又有什么影响呢？
Yeah, you're never going to hash anything to an odd-numbered slot.
对了 你永远不可能哈希映射到一个奇数位的槽
You wasted half your slots.
你浪费了一半的槽
It doesn't matter what the key distribution is.
这并不关系到键的分布状况
OK, as long as they're all even, OK,
只要它们都是偶数的
that means the odds slots are never used.
那就意味着奇数位的槽没用了
OK, an extreme example, here's another example,
另外一个极端的例子
imagine that m is equal to two to the r.
假设 m = 2^r
In other words, all its factors are small divisors, OK?
也就是说 它所有的因子等于我们的小除数d
In that case, if I think about taking k mod m
在这种情况下 如果让k对m取余
OK, the hash doesn't even depend on all the bits of k, OK?
它的哈希过程中就不会考虑到k所有的位（二进制）
So, for example, suppose I had one..., and r equals six,
就譬如我定义了这个二进制数...r=6
OK, so m is two to the sixth.
那么m=2^6
So, I take this binary number,
我用这串二进制数值
mod two to the sixth, what's the hash value?
对2^6取余的哈希值是多少？
If I take something mod a power of two, what does it do?
如果对2的幂取余 会发生什么情况？
So, I hash this function. This is k, OK, in binary.
我对这个k的二进制数计算它的哈希值
And I take it mod two to the sixth.
也就是拿它对2^6取余
Well, if I took it mod two, what's the answer?
如果拿它除以2取余 结果是多少？
What's this number mod two? Zero, right.
这个数对2取余等于多少？ 对，是0
OK, what's this number mod four? One zero.
对4取余呢？ 是10（二进制）
What is it mod two to the sixth?
除以2^6取余呢？
Yeah, it's just these last six bits. This is H of k.
对，就是最后这6位数 这就是h(k)
OK, when you take something mod a power of two,
当你对2的幂取余时
all you're doing is taking its low order bits.
你其实就是在取它（二进制）后几位的数字
OK, mod two to the r, you are taking its r low order bits.
对2^r取余的结果 就等于它最低的r位数字
So, the hash function doesn't even depend on what's up here.
这样的话 哈希函数就与键值的其他几位数无关了
So, that's a pretty bad situation
这是很糟糕的状况
because generally you would like a very common regularity
因为通常来说 二进制数据都具有一个常见的规则性
that you'll see in data is that all the low order bits are the same,
要么所有的低位数字相同、高位不同
and all the high order bits differ, or vice versa.
要么反过来 所有的高位的数字相同、低位不同
So, this particular is not a very good one.
所以这种状况就并不是很好
So, good heuristics for this is to pick m to be a prime,
所以好的方法是取质数来作为m的值
not too close to a power of two or ten
不要太接近2的幂或10的幂这些数
because those are the two common bases
因为2和10是全世界最常见的底数
that you see regularity in the world.
也是最有规则性的底数
A prime is sometimes inconvenient, however.
质数有时候也不是很好确定
But generally, it's fairly easy to find primes.
但总体上 质数并不难找
And there's a lot of nice theorems about primes.
有很多关于质数的好定理
So, generally what you do, if you're just coding up something
如果你只是平常地编写代码
and you know what it is, you can pick a prime out of a textbook
你知道要选怎么选哈希表大小  你就可以选用书本里的质数
or look it up on the web or write a little program,
或者上网查阅、写个小程序之类的
or whatever, and pick a prime.
只要选出一个质数就好
Not too close to a power of two or ten,
不要用太接近以2或10为底的数
and it will probably work pretty well.
它就很可能有效地运行了
It will probably work pretty well.
可能还运行得相当不错
So, this is a very popular method, the division method.
上述是一个非常流行的方法 “除法哈希法”
OK, but the next method we are going to see
下一个我们要学习的算法
is actually usually superior.
会更加的出色
The reason people do this is because
人们使用“除法哈希法”是因为
they can write in-line in their code.
它能方便地嵌入代码里
OK, but it's not usually the best method.
但它不是最好的算法
And the reason is because division,
原因之一是
one of the reasons is division tends to take a lot of cycles
相对于乘法和加法而言
to compute on most computers compared with multiplication or addition.
在很多计算机上运算时 除法往往有更多的循环运算
OK, in fact, it's usually done with taking several multiplications.
而实际上 我们通常用几步乘法就能解决问题
So, the next method is actually generally better,
所以 我们下面要介绍算法会更好用一些
but none of the hash function methods that we are talking about today are,
但其实我们今天所提到的哈希算法
in some sense, provably good hash functions.
在某种意义上 都不能说是好的哈希函数
OK, so for the multiplication method,
对于“乘法哈希法”
the nice thing about it is just essentially requires multiplication to do.
它的优点是 基本上只需要用到乘法运算
And, for that is, also, we are going to assume that
同样地 我们也要先定些假设条件
the number of slots is a power of two which is also often very convenient.
槽的数量m 是以2为底的幂数 这对后面运算有利
OK, and for this, we're going to assume that the computer has w bit words.
同时我们还要假定计算机的一个字的长度是w位
So, it would be convenient on a computer with 32 bits,
比如 比较合适的计算机的字长有32位的
or 64 bits, for example.
或者64位的
OK, this would be very convenient.
这都是比较好算的
So, the hash function is the following. h of k
这个哈希函数是这样的...
is equal to A times k mod, two to the w, right shifted by w minus r.
h（k）=（A·k mod 2^w）rsh（w-r）
OK, so the key part of this is A,
关键的地方是这里的A
which has chosen to be an odd integer in the range
A是一个奇数
between two to the w minus one and two to the w.
一个大于2^(w-r)  小于2^w的一个奇数
OK, so it's an odd integer that the full width of the computer word.
它是一个等长于计算机字长的奇数
OK, and what you do is multiply it by whatever your key is,
无论你的键值是什么 把它与A相乘
by this funny integer. And, then take it mod two to the w.
乘以这个有趣的整数 然后对2^w取余
And then, you take the result and right shift it
最后得出的结果 再向右移一定的位数
by this fixed amount, w minus r.
偏移w-r的位数
So, this is a bit wise right shift.
“rsh”指二进制位运算的右偏移
OK, so let's look at what this does.
让们分析一下这函数在做什么
But first, let me just give you a couple of tips on how you pick,
但我先教你们一些如何选择A的值
or what you don't pick for A.
或不要选哪些值作为A的值
So, you don't pick A too close to a power of two.
首先A的取值不要太接近以2为底的数
And, it's generally a pretty fast method
这是一个快速的算法
because multiplication mod two to the w is faster than division.
因为相乘后再对2^w取余 比除法要快
And the other thing is that a right shift is fast,
还有一点是 右移运算也很快
especially because this is a known shift.
尤其是我们已经知道了偏移量是多少
OK, you know it before you are computing the hash function.
在你运算这个哈希函数前
Both w and r are known in advance.
你已经提前知道了w和r的值
So, the compiler can often do tricks there to make it go even faster.
所以编译器也有些提高运算速度的方法
So, let's do an example to understand how this hash function works.
那我们举个例子 来理解这个哈希函数的运作
So, we will have, in this case, a number of slots will be eight,
在这个例子里 我们有8个槽
which is two to the three.
8=2^3
And, we'll have a bizarre word size of seven bits.
我们取一个特殊的字长为7位
Anybody know any seven bit computers out there?
有人见过世界上哪台计算机的字长是7位的吗？
OK, well, here's one.
这里就有一台
So, A is our fixed value that's used for hashing all our keys.
A是一个用于哈希函数的定值
And, in this case, let's say it's 1011001.
假定 A=1011001
So, that's A. And, I take in some value for k that I'm going to multiply.
我选取一个k值来乘以A
So, k is going to be 1101011. So, that's my k.
我设定k值为1101011
And, I multiply them.
用A乘以k
What I multiply two, each of these is the full word width.
这两个值恰好都占一个字长
You can view it as the full word width of the machine,
你可以将它们看成计算机里的两个字
in this case, seven bits.
在这里 都是7位
So, in general, this would be like a 32 bit number,
不过通常的计算机里 这些应该是32位的数
and my key, I'd be multiplying two 32 bit numbers, for example.
所以这应该是两个32位数的乘法运算
OK, and so, when I multiply that out, I get a 2w bit answer.
这里乘法运算会得出一个2w位的答案
So, when you multiply two w bit numbers, you get a 2w bit answer.
当你用两个w位的数相乘时 你会得到一个2w位的答案
In this case, it happens to be that number, OK?
这个例子里 乘积是这个
So, that's the product part, OK?
这些是乘积部分
And then we take it mod two to the w.
然后再拿它对2^w取余
Well, what mod two to the w says is that I'm just taking,
对2^w取余也是意味着
ignoring the high order bits of this product.
忽略掉这乘积的高位
So, all of these are ignored,
这几位数都忽略掉
because, remember that if I take something, mod, a power of two,
要记住 当一个数对以2为底的幂取余时
that's just the low order bits.
得到的是该数低位的值
So, I just get these low order bits as being the mod.
所以取余的结果是这几个低位的值
And then, the right shift operation, and that's good also, by the way,
再然后是右偏移运算 同样也是很方便
because a lot of machines, when I multiply two 32 bit numbers,
因为大部分的计算机里 当我用两个32位数相乘时
they'll have an instruction that gives you just the 32 lower bits.
计算机会有一个指令会直接得出32个低位的值
And, it's usually an instruction
所以使用这种指令
that's faster than the instruction that gives you the full 64 bit answer.
通常会比先算64位结果要快很多
OK, so, that's very convenient.
所以 它用起来非常方便的
And, the second thing is, then, that I want just the,
因为我想要的只是...
in this case, three bits that are the high order bits of this word.
这个字长的前3位的值
So, this ends up being my H of k.
这个就是h(k)
And these end up getting removed by right shifting this word over.
所以我们用右移运算移走其他的位
So, you just right shift that in, zeros come in, in a high order bit,
将右边低位移走 在高位填充0
and you end up getting that value of H of k.
最后得到h(k)的值
OK, so to understand what's going on here,
怎么理解这个运算过程
why this is a pretty good method, or what's happening with it,
为什么这是一个很精彩的算法 它到底做了什么
you can imagine that one way to think about it
你可以这样想
is to think of A as being a binary fraction.
把A看作一个二进制的分数
So, imagine that the decimal point is here, sorry, the binary point,
想像小数点在这里 哦不 是二进制小数点
OK, the radix point is here.
小数点在这里
Then when I multiply things, I'm just taking,
当A乘以某个数时
the binary point ends up being there.
小数点就会出现在这里
OK, so if you just imagine that conceptually,
你只需要大概地想像一下
we don't have to actually put this into the hardware
没必要把这些放入计算机里
because we just do what the hardware does.
因为这只是帮助我们理解而已
But, I can imagine that it's there, and that it's here.
我可以想像 这边是小数部分 那个是整数部分
And so, what I'm really taking is the fractional part of this product
我们真正需要的是这个乘积的小数部分
if I treat A as a fraction of a number.
要把A看成一个数的小数部分
So, we can certainly look at that as sort of a modular wheel.
我们可以“车轮法”来理解这个哈希函数
So, here I have a wheel where this is going to be,
我们画一个车轮
that I'm going to divide into eight parts,
将它等分成八部分
OK, where this point is zero.
这个点代表0
And then, I go around, and this point is then one.
然后我走了一圈 这个点变成1
And, I go around, and this point is two, and so forth,
我再走一圈 这个点是2 依此类推
so that all the integers, if I wrap it around this unit wheel,
如果我绕着这个单位车轮转
all the integers lined up at the zero point here, OK?
所有的整数都和这个零点连成一线
And then, we can divide this into the fractional pieces.
然后我们可以用分数把车轮划分成几块
So, that's essentially the zero point. This is the one eighth,
这原本是零点 这里是八分之一
because we are dividing into eight, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
因为我们把车轮等分成八份 2、3、4...7
So, if I have one times A, in this case,
如果我用1乘以A
I'm basically saying, well, one times A,
用上述例子的A 乘以1
if I multiply, is basically going around
基本上是这样绕的
to about there, five and a half I think, right,
大概到这里 我想是5.5
because one times A is about five and a half,
因为1乘以A大约等于5.5
OK, or five halves of... 5.5 eighths, essentially.
差不多是5.5/8
So, it takes me about to there. That's A.
大概到这里 这是A
And, if I do 2^A, that continues around,
如果我算2A 那继续绕
and takes me up to about, where?
大概会到这里
About, a little past three, about to there.
稍微超过3 大概在这里
So, that's 2^A. OK, and 3^A takes me, then,
这是2A 然后是3A
around to somewhere like about there.
大概是绕到这里
So, each time I add another A,
每次我加多一个A
it's taking me another A's distance around.
它会加多一段A的弧长
And, the idea is that if A is, for example, odd,
我想说的是 如果A是奇数
and it's not too close to a power of two,
不是近似以2为底的幂值
then what's happening is sort of throwing it
那哈希的过程 就可以看成是
into another slot on a different thing.
将键扔进不同的槽
So, if I now go around, if I have k being very big,
类似绕车轮 如果k值特别大
then k times A is going around k times.
那k乘以A 将相当于绕k个圈
Where does it end up?
在哪里停下呢？
It's like spinning a wheel of fortune or something.
这就像是在转动一个幸运轮盘
OK, it ends somewhere. OK, and so that's basically the notion.
会在某个地方停下  这些是基本的概念
That's basically the notion, that it's going to end up in some place.
它最终将在某个地方停下
So, you're basically looking at, where does k·a end up?
你就想知道 它会在哪个位置停下呢？
Well, it sort of whirls around, and ends up at some point.
它就这样转啊转 最后停在某个地方
OK, and so that's why that tends to be a fairly good one.
这也是为什么 这是个不错的哈希函数
But, these are only heuristic methods for hashing,
不过这只是探索性的哈希方法
because for any hash function,
因为对于任意哈希函数而言
you can always find a set of keys that's going to make it operate badly.
你总能找到一些键 使得哈希出来的结果很糟糕
So, the question is, well, what do you use in practice?
问题是 你在实际应用中选择哪个
OK, the second topic that I want to tie it,
我想说的第二个话题
so, we talked about resolving collisions by chaining.
我们讨论过用链接法 来解决碰撞问题
OK, there's another way of resolving collisions, which is often useful,
其实还有别外一个解决碰撞的方法 也是很有用的
which is resolving collisions by what's called open addressing.
这个用来解决碰撞的方法 称为“开放寻址法”
OK, and the idea is, in this method, is we have no storage for links.
在这个方法里 我们没有链表
So, when I result by chaining,
如果我们用链接法
I'd need an extra linked field in each record
为了做到这一点 在每个记录里
in order to be able to do that.
就需要一个额外的关联地址
Now, that's not necessarily a big overhead, but for some applications,
但对于某些应用来说 就没必要为此付出巨大的开支
I don't want to have to touch those records at all.
我们也不想对记录做有任何的改动
OK, and for those, open addressing is a useful way to resolve collisions.
在这种情况下 开放寻址法就是解决碰撞的很有效的方法
So, the idea is, with open addressing, is if I hash to a given slot,
用开放寻址法的时候 如果我哈希到一个槽
and the slot is full, OK, what I do is
但这个槽已经存放了记录 没关系
I just hash again with a different hash function,
我就用另外一个哈希函数再哈希一次
with my second hash function.
我用第二个哈希函数
I check that slot. OK, if that slot is full,
再哈希到下一个槽 如果那个也满了
OK, then I hash again.
那再哈希一次
And, I keep this probe sequence,
形成一个探查的序列
which hopefully is a permutation
然后变成一种算术排列
so that I'm not going back and checking things that
使得我不用探查那些我已经查找过的槽
I've already checked until I find a place to put it.
直到找到一个可以放置的地方为止
And, if I got a good probe sequence that I will hopefully,
如果用一个好的探查序列
then, find a place to put it fairly quickly.
我就能快速地找到一个放置的地方
OK, and then to search, I just follow the same probe sequence.
对于查找键值而言 我们就按同样的探查序列来查找
So, the idea, here, is we probe the table systematically
开放寻址的思想就是  系统地探查哈希表
until an empty slot is found, OK?
直到找到一个空的槽为止
And so, we can extend that by looking
我们可以把它扩展开来看
as if the sequence of hash functions were, in fact,
如果哈希函数的序列是...
a hash function that took two arguments: a key and a probe step.
实际上 一个哈希函数有两个参数 键和探查顺序
In other words, is it the zero of one our first one?
换句话说 这是第一个哈希函数
It's the second one, etc. So, it takes two arguments.
第二个函数...等等 它有两个参数
So, H is then going to map our universe of keys cross,
哈希函数h会全域里的键
our probe number into a slot.
通过一步步的探查映射到槽里
So, this is the universe of keys. This is the probe number.
U代表键的全域 这些是探查号
And, this is going to be the slot.
这段表示槽
Now, as I mentioned, the probe sequence should be permutation.
正如我之前提到的 探查序列应该是一个算术排列
In other words, it should just be the numbers from zero
换句话说 它必须是数字0到m-1的
to n minus one in some fairly random order.
某种完全随机的排列
OK, it should just be rearranged.
对 把它们打乱重排
And the other thing about open addressing is that
另外 对于开放寻址表来说...
you don't have to worry about n chaining is that
你不必担心n链接的问题
the table may actually fill up.
因为哈希表最终会被填满
So, you have to have that the number of elements in the table
所以哈希表里元素的数量
is less than or equal to the table size,
必须小于表的大小
the number of slots because the table may fill up.
小于槽的数量 这样才不会溢出
And, if it's full, you're going to probe everywhere.
但如果哈希表已经满了 无论怎么探查
You are never going to get a place to put it.
你都不可能找到一个地方来存放数据
And, the final thing is that in this type of scheme,
所以 在这种规划类型中
deletion is difficult. It's not impossible.
删除变得非常困难的 但不是不可能
There are schemes for doing deletion.
有专门的删除方案
But, it's basically hard because the danger is that
但删除操作执行起来比较困难 因为有这样的风险..
you remove a key out of the table, and now,
当你从表中移除某个键后
somebody who's doing a probe sequence who would have hit that key
有人按探查序列来查找另一个键  他本应先发现这里不是他要的键
and gone to find his element now finds that it's an empty slot.
继而再向下查找 然而现在却发现这个槽是空的
And he says, oh, the key I am looking for probably isn't there.
那么他会认会 想查找的键很有可能不在这个表里
OK, so you have that issue to deal with.
对 你会碰到的问题
So, you can delete things but keep them marked,
那么你可以将之删除 但在槽里留下标记
and there's all kinds of schemes that people have for doing deletion.
人们有各种各样的方案来做删除操作
But it's difficult. It's messy compared to chaining,
但都比较困难 链接法直接从链表里删除键就好了
where you can just remove the element out of the chain.
相比之下 这种删除操作很混乱
So, let's do an example
我们举一个例子
-- -- just so that we make sure we're on the same page.
——来保证大家都跟得上
So, we'll insert a key. k is 496. OK, so here's my table.
插入一个键k=496 这是哈希表
And, I've got some values in it, 586, 133, 204, 481, etc.
里面有一些数值 586、133、204、481等等
So, the table looks like that; the other places are empty.
哈希表是这样的 其它的地方是空的
So, on my zero step, I probe H of 496, zero. OK,
第零号探查，我们探查 h(496,0)
and let's say that takes me to the slot where there's 204.
假设我们哈希映射到这个槽 这里已经有数值204
And so, I say, oh, there's something there.
好，我们发现这个槽已经有记录了
I have to probe again. So then, I probe H of 496, one.
那就必须再探查一次 探查h(496,1)
Maybe that maps me there, and I discover,
可能映射到这里 我发现——
oh, there's something there.
这个槽也被占用了
So, now, I probe H of 496, two.
现在我探查h(496,2)
Maybe that takes me to there. It's empty.
可能映射到这里 一个空槽
So, if I'm doing a search, I report nil.
如果是进行查找操作 那么返回nil
If I'm doing in the insert, I put it there.
如果是进行插入操作 则把键放入这个槽
And then, if I'm looking for that value, if I put it there,
如果要查找一个已经放在这里的值
then when I'm looking, I go through exactly the same sequence.
在探查过程中 我就完全按照同样序列来查找
I'll find these things are busy, and then, eventually,
发现这些位置都被占用了 最终——
I'll come up and discover the value.
查到这里 找到了这个值
OK, and there are various heuristics that people use, as well,
人们还会使用多种探索性技巧
like keeping track of the longest probe sequence
像追踪最长探查序列
because there's no point in probing beyond the largest number of probes
因为查找操作的探查次数 不可能多于...
that need to be done globally to do an insertion.
所有插入操作中所用的最大的探查次数
OK, so if it took me 5,
如果用了5次探查
5 is the maximum number of probes I ever did for an insertion.
5是做插入操作时 用到的最大的探查次数
A search never has to look more than five,
那一个查找序列最多不会超过5个
OK, and so sometimes hash tables will keep that auxiliary value
因此有时哈希表会附加 额外的数据
so that it can quit rather than continuing to probe
这样它能及时结束 而不用保持探查序列
until it doesn't find something.
结果却什么都找不到
OK, so, search is the same probe sequence.
搜索也是用同样的探查序列
And, if it's successful, it finds the record.
如果成功 则返回相应记录
And, if it's unsuccessful, you find a nil.
如果不成功 则返回nil
OK, so it's pretty straightforward.
相当直观
So, once again, as with just hash functions to begin with,
那么 就像刚刚哈希函数那样
there are a lot of ideas about how you should form a probe sequence,
如何构造探查序列，如何有效进行探查
ways of doing this effectively.
也是有各种各样的方法
OK, so the simplest one is called linear probing,
其中最简单的 叫做“线性探查”
and what you do there is you have H of k comma i.
线性探查的意思是
You just make that be some H prime of k, zero plus i mod m.
让h(k,i）等于（h'(k,0）+ i) mod m
Sorry, no prime there. OK, so what happens is,
不好意思 这里没有撇号
so, the idea here is that all you are doing on the I'th probe is,
我们的想法是 在第i次探查时...
on the zero'th probe, you look at H of k zero.
在第0号探查时 你找的是h(k,0)
On probe one, you just look at the slot after that.
第1号探查 只要查找h(k,0)的下一个槽
Probe two, you look at the slot after that.
第2号探查 继续查找再下一个槽
So, you're just simply, rather than sort of jumping around like this,
这样 相对于跳跃性地探查 你只需要简单地一个个探查
you probe there and then just find the next one that will fit in.
探查到一个位置 然后接下去一个一个查找
OK, so you just scan down mod m.
持续往下扫描 最后对m取余
So, if you hit the bottom, you go to the top.
这样的话 如果查到表底 又会转回顶部
OK, so the I'th one, so that's fairly easy to do
这个真的很容易运作
because you don't have to recomputed a full hash function each time.
因为你并不需要 每次都重新算一次哈希函数
All you have to do is add one each time you go
你所要做的 是每次探查都加多一个1
because the difference between this and the previous one is just one.
因为跟之前的函数的差别只是1
OK, so you just go down.
你只要往下探查
Now, the problem with that is that you get a phenomenon of clustering.
但也存在一个问题 叫做“群集现象”
If you get a few things in a given area, then suddenly everything,
如果一串连续区域同时被占用了 那接下来所有的操作
everybody has to keep searching to the end of those things.
都必须不停探查 直至这串区域的底部
OK, so that turns out not to be one of the better schemes,
这样看来这个方案并不是太好
although it's not bad if you just need to do something quick and dirty.
尽管不算很差 如果你只是做一些“豆腐渣”程序的话
So, it suffers from primary clustering,
它会遇到“一次群集”的问题
where regions of the hash table get very full.
就是哈希表的某个区间会被占满
And then, anything that hashes into that region
任何映射到这段区间的键
has to look through all the stuff that's there.
都必须探查遍历 这段里所有的槽
OK, so: long runs of filled slots.
连续被占有的槽 也会越来越长
OK, there's also things like quadratic clustering,
也有一种情况叫“二次群集”
where you basically make this be,
主要区别是
instead of adding one each time, you add i each time.
每次加的是i而不是1
OK, but probably the most effective popular scheme
而也许最有效率、最受欢迎的设计方案
is what's called double hashing.
叫“二次哈希”
And, you can do statistical studies.
你可以做一下统计分析
People have done statistical studies to show that this is a good scheme, OK,
人们通过统计分析 证明这是一个不错的方案
where you let H of k, i, let me do it below here because I have for them.
让h(k，i）...写到下面去 这样才有足够地方写
So, H of k, i is equal to an H_1 of k plus i times H_2 of k.
h(k，i)=(h_1(k)+i*h_2(k)）mod m
So, you have two hash functions on m.
你有两个关于m的哈希函数
You have two hash functions, H_1 of k and H_2 of k.
两个哈希函数分别是h_1(k)和h_2(k)
OK, so you compute the two hash functions,
计算这两个哈希函数
and what you do is you start by just using H_1 of k for the zero probe,
开始你只用h_1(k)来做0号探查
because here, i, then, will be zero. OK.
因为这里i会等于0
Then, for the probe number one, OK, you just add H_2 of k.
然后对于1号探查 加上h_2(k)
For probe number two, you just add that hash function amount again.
对于2号探查 加上原来的哈希函数值
You just keep adding H_2 of k for each successive probe you make.
这样每次成功的探查 都只需要再加上h_2(k)
So, it's fairly easy; you compute two hash functions up front,
这很简单 预先运算前两个哈希函数
OK, or you can delay the second one, in case.
或者保险起见 第二个函数可以推迟计算
But basically, you compute two up front,
但最基本上 是把两个函数值都计算好
and then you just keep adding the second one in.
然后不断地叠加第二个函数值
You start at the location of the first one,
从第一个哈希到的位置开始
and keep adding the second one, mod m,
不断加上第二个哈希值 同时对m取余
to determine your probe sequences.
来决定你的探查序列
So, this is an excellent method.
这是一个优秀的方法
OK, it does a fine job, and you usually pick m to be a power of two here,
它能完成不错的工作 通常把m取为以2为底的幂值
OK, so that you're using,
这样来使用
usually people use this with the multiplication method, for example,
比如 通常人们会结合乘法哈希法一起使用
so that m is a power of two,
这里m是以2为底的值
and H_2 of k you force to be odd.
h_2(k)选择奇数的值
OK, so we don't use and even value there,
在这里不使用偶数
because otherwise for any particular key, you'd be skipping over.
因为那样对于某些特殊键 会直接跳过某些槽
Once again, you would have the problem that everything could be even,
再说一次 你可能会遇到这样的问题 所有的数值都是偶数
or everything could be odd as you're going through.
或者所有的数值都是奇数
But, if you make H_2 of k odd, and m is a power of two,
如果让h_2(k)是奇数 让m是2为底的幂数
you are guaranteed to hit every slot.
你能保证所有槽都被分配到
OK, so let's analyze this scheme.
分析一下这个框架
This turns out to be a pretty interesting scheme to analyze.
看起来是一个很有意思的框架
It's got some nice math in it.
里面有一些美好的数学元素
So, once again, in the worst case, hashing is lousy.
再一次说到最坏情况... 哈希不是完美的
So, we're going to analyze average case.
分析一下平均情况
OK, and for this, we need a little bit  stronger assumption than for chaining.
为了这个分析 我们要假设的东西比“链接法”还要多一点
And, we call it the assumption of uniform hashing,
这里的假设叫“均匀哈希”
which says that each key is equally likely,
所有键都均等地
OK, to have any one of the m factorial permutations
有 m! 种探查序列
as its probe sequence, independent of other keys.
而且每个键都是相互独立的
And, the theorem we're going to prove
我们将要证明的理论是
is that the expected number of probes is,
预期的探查次数
at most, one over one minus alpha if alpha is less than one,
最多不超过1/(1-α) 如果α小于1
OK, that is, if the number of keys in the table is less than number of slots.
这也意味着 哈希表里键的数量小于槽的数量
OK, so we're going to show that
好 我们要证明的就是
the number of probes is one over one minus alpha.
探查次数等于1/(1-α)
So, alpha is the load factor, and of course,
α是装载因子
for open addressing, we want the load factor to be less than one
当然 对于开放寻址法 我们要求装载因子小于1
because if we have more keys than slots,
因为如果我们的键数大于槽数
open addressing simply doesn't work, OK,
开放寻址法就不起作用了
because you've got to find a place for every key in the table.
因为你必须要为每个键都在哈希表找一个槽
So, the proof, we'll look at an unsuccessful search, OK?
那先来看一个失败搜索的案例
So, the first thing is that one probe is always necessary.
首先 第一次探查必不可少
OK, so if I have n over m, sorry, if I have n items stored in m slots,
如果有n/m 不好意思 如果n个项存放在m个槽里
what's the probability that when I do that probe
探查过程碰撞到
I get a collision with something that's already in the table?
一个已经被占用的槽的概率是多少？
What's the probability that I get a collision?
发生碰撞的概率是多少？
Yeah? Yeah, n over m, right?
对 就是n/m
So, with probability, n over m, we have a collision
所以 发生碰撞的概率是n/m
because my table has got n things in there.
因为哈希表有n个项在里面
I'm hashing, at random, to one of them.
随机哈希其中一个
OK, so, what are the odds I hit something, n over m?
撞上某一个的概率是多少？n/m
And then, a second probe is necessary.
然后 第二次探查也是必须的
OK, so then, I do a second probe.
进行第二次探查
And, with what probability on the second probe do I get a collision?
第二次探查发生碰撞的概率是多少？
So, we're going to make the assumption of uniform hashing.
这里就要用到“均匀哈希”的假设了
Each key is equally likely to
因为每个键都均等地
have any one of the m factorial permutations as its probe sequence.
有 m! 种探查序列
So, what is the probability that on the second probe,
那么 第二次探查发生碰撞的概率...
OK, I get a collision?
会是多少？
[Professor]Yeah? If it's a permutation, you're not, right?
[教授]这是一种排列 是吧？（？）
Something like that. What is it exactly?
差不多 但具体是多少呢？
So, that's the question.
那是问题所在
OK, so you are not going to hit the same slot
你不会撞上同一个槽
because it's going to be a permutation. Yeah?
因为这是一个排列
That's exactly right. n minus one over m minus one
完全正确 (n-1)/(m-1)
because I'm now,
因为现在
I've essentially eliminated that slot that I hit the first time.
我已经把第一次发生碰撞的槽 给排除掉了
And so, I have, now, and there was a key there.
那现在 我们已经和一个键碰撞过了
So, now I'm essentially looking, at random,
那其他的n-1个键
into the remaining m minus one slots
就随机地分布在
where there are aggregately n minus one keys in those slots.
剩下的m-1个槽里
OK, everybody got that?
大家都理解了？
OK, so with that probability, I get a collision.
按照这样的概率 发生了碰撞
That means that I need a third probe necessary, OK?
那意味着我们需要第三次探查
And, we keep going on. OK, so what is it going to be the next time?
那照这样下去 下一次的碰撞概率是多少？
Yeah, it's going to be n minus two over m minus two.
对  它变成(n-2)/(m-2)
So, let's note, OK, that n minus i over m minus i
我们注意到(n-i)/(m-i)
is less than n over m, which equals alpha, OK?
小于n/m 也就是小于α
So, n minus i over m minus i is less than n over m.
至于为什么 (n-i)/(m-i) < n/m
And, the way you can sort of reason that is that
你可以这样理解
if n is less than m, I'm subtracting a larger fraction of n
如果n < m，虽然同样是减去i
when I subtract i than I am subtracting a fraction of m.
但是n减少的比例 却比m减少的比例要多
OK, so therefore, n minus i over m minus i
因此 (n-i)/(m-i)
is going to be less than n over m.
就会比n/m小
OK, so, or you can do the algebra.
你也可以尝试下做一下代数运算
I think it's always helpful when you do algebra
我认为当你思考问题或
to sort of think about it sort of quantitatively as well,
进行数量运算时 代数分析总是有帮助的
you know, qualitatively what's going on.
它会定性同时也定量地让你理解所发生的事
So, the expected number of probes is,
那预期探查数就是...
then, going to be equal to, it's going to be equal to
会等于...
because we're going to need some space, well,
因为我们需要点空间 所以
we have one which is forced because we've got to do one probe,
必须是1 因为要有第一次探查
plus with probability n over m,
加上概率n/m
I have to do another probe plus with probability of n over m minus one
还需要一次探查 加上概率(n-1)/(m-1)
I have to do another probe
继续另外一个探查...
up until I do one plus one over m minus n.
直到1+1/(m-n)
OK, so each one is cascading what's happened.
每一步都有连锁的影响
In the book, there is a more rigorous proof
课本里有使用指标随机变量
of this using indicator random variables.
来做的更严谨的证明
I'm going to give you the short version.
我这里给出的是简单的版本
OK, so basically, this is my first probe.
这是第一次探查
With probability n over m, I had to do a second one.
我有n/m的概率 要进行第二次探查
And, the result of that is that
而这一次探查的结果是
with probability n minus one over m minus one, I have to do another.
有(n-1)/(m-1)的概率 必须进行下一步探查
And, with probability n over two minus m over two,
然后 我又有(n-2)/(m-2)的概率发生碰撞
I have to do another, and so forth.
必须再进行下一个探查 以此类推
So, that's how many probes I'm going to end up doing.
这就是我最后要探查的次数
So, this is less than or equal to one plus alpha.
这条式子小于或等于
There's one plus alpha times one plus alpha times one plus alpha,
1+α(1+α(1+α(...1+α)))...
OK, just using the fact that I had here.
这要用到刚才所述的内容
OK, and that is less than or equal to one plus I just multiply through here.
这些小于或等于1+α...我把它们乘出来
Alpha plus alpha squared plus alpha cubed plus k.
α+1+α^2+α^3+...
I can just take that out to infinity. It's going to bound this.
这式子能无限写下去 做为上面式子的上限
OK, does everybody see the math there?
大家都看到这些数学式了吗？
OK, and that is just the sum, I, equals zero to infinity,
然后全部加起来 从0到正无穷
alpha to the I, which is equal to one over one minus alpha
最终等于1/(1-α)
using your familiar geometric series bound.
用你熟悉的几何数列上限
OK, and there's also, in the textbook, an analysis of the successful search,
同样的 课本里也有成功搜索的分析
which, once again, is a little bit more technical
同样的 成功搜索的分析也需要一点技巧性
because you have to worry about what the distribution is that
因为当要搜索的东西 已经存在于哈希表里
you happen to have in the table
你就要考虑在哈希表里...
when you are searching for something that's already in the table.
它的分布是怎样
But, it turns out it's also bounded by one over one minus alpha.
但结果依然是1/(1-α)
So, let's just look to see what that means.
好 我们看看这式子意味着什么
So, if alpha is less than one is a constant,
如果α< 1 而且是一个常数量
it implies that it takes order one probes.
意味着需要O(1)步探查
OK, so if alpha is a constant, it takes order one probes.
如果α是一个常数量 需要O(1)步探查
OK, but it's helpful to understand what's happening with the constant.
但最好还是理解常数量的到底是个怎么样的状况
So, for example, if the table is 50% full, so alpha is a half,
举个例子 如果哈希表一半是满的 α是0.5
what's the expected number of probes by this analysis?
从上述分析来看 预期探查数是多少?
Two, because one over one minus a half is two.
2次 因为1/(1-0.5)等于2
If I let the table fill up to 90%, how many probes do I need on average?
如果哈希表填充了90%的槽 平均需要多少次探查？
Ten. So, you can see that as you fill up the table,
10次 所以你可以看到 随着哈希表的密度增大
the cost is going dramatically, OK?
探查的时间花费会急剧地增加
And so, typically, you don't let the table get too full.
所以 一般不要让哈希表 太过稠密
OK, you don't want to be pushing 99.9% utilization.
没必要要求99.9%的利用率
Oh, I got this great hash table that's got full utilization.
虽然我有一个哈希表 利用率百分之百
It's like, yeah, and it's slow. It's really, really slow,
是啊 但它很慢 真的很慢很慢
OK, because as alpha approaches one,
因为随着α逼近1
the time is approaching and essentially m, or n.
运行时间会趋近m或者n
Good. So, next time, we are going to
好的 那下一节课 我们将讨论
address head-on in what was one of the most,
什么是算法里最...
I think, interesting ideas in algorithms.
有意思的想法
We are going to talk about how you solve this problem
我们将讨论 如何解决以下问题：
that no matter what hash function you pick,there's a bad set of keys.
无论你选择何种哈希函数 总有一个不适宜的键集
OK, so next time we're going to show that there are ways
下一次我们将介绍几种非常精彩的...
of confronting that problem, very clever ways.
用来应对这种问题的方法
And we use a lot of math for it so will be a really fun lecture.
到时会用到很多数学技巧 应该是很有意思的一节课